is it wrong to judge others
and are we supposed to be aiming for
that
non-judgmental attitude towards
everything well that's impossible abstaining from a
well that's impossible abstaining from a
judgment
is your judgment that's how you're
judging it
so the question is not whether you
should not judge others
the question is whether you should do it
with or without ill will
and that's what the problem is the
problem is not that you judge and
discriminate that's what the nature of
mind is
thoughts are already forms of
discrimination i want this i don't want
that it's like whether you whether they're
it's like whether you whether they're
fueled by ill will
that's what you don't want but if you're
factually judging the behavior of some person that
judging the behavior of some person that
is that is a fact
but if on account of that fact you feel
superior start involving your conceit
you feel that inferior again start
involving your conceit
you feel righteous uh you feel ill will
hatred irritation towards them that's why
irritation towards them that's why
you're wrong not because there is a
thought of judging and discriminating
between agreeable disagreeable right or wrong
agreeable disagreeable right or wrong
but it's it's harder to differentiate
problem on that level because it's more
personal and more kind of unpleasant as
well and also more ambiguous to work on your
and also more ambiguous to work on your
conceits
and like whatever emotional background
of it
it's much harder than to just okay i'll
just remove the thoughts i just will not
judge but that now makes you sacrifice your
but that now makes you sacrifice your
own intellect your own mind
so then what you don't judge the clearly
moral unwholesome
deluded behavior you pretend it's fine
because you didn't know how to deal with
the problem of it that you were
experiencing that's just a lazy attempt of of of
that's just a lazy attempt of of of
trying to deal with the issue
so you have to recognize the mind judges
yourself and others that's what the mind
does picks
and chooses and discriminates but do you
feel superior economy that's your
problem so don't feel superior on
account of your thoughts
don't feed them don't entertain them
don't indulge them
do you feel ill will on account of your
thoughts sing don't welcome it don't
entertain it don't indulge it
then you just have thought then if that
thought was fueled solely by your real
will once you stop fueling the world the
once you stop fueling the world the
thought will disappear
if the thought was also factual
recognition of the state of affairs
in terms of this person's behavior of
that person behavior
your ill will will disappear but the
recognition of reality will not
disappear and
they are behaving like a foolish immoral
person i don't want to associate with
them i wish them all the best nothing i don't
i wish them all the best nothing i don't
have any
will or hatred or wishing harm
and cruelty as the buddha would say but
that doesn't mean you're a blind at fool
now that doesn't discriminate between
different types of behavior
different types of people different sets
of values in the world
so there's the encouragement to ready to
be able to define
what is wholesome and unwholesome
and not to deny that those are factors
that need to be discerned exactly yeah
take responsibility for it so if
something is wholesome or unwholesome
you are responsible in
how you feel about it so to speak why
because your feelings they make you act they
your feelings they make you act they
make you do stuff
so are you restrained in regard to your
feelings or do you feel fully justified
in regard to them
and that's that kind of sense of
righteousness when people are like
righteously indignant and and full on
ill will
but they fully feel righteous and
wholesome because this behavior is wrong
yes but that doesn't justify the extent
of your real will now
that behavior is wrong in itself full
stop that's where it ends
but you feeling superior having your
will on account of it
that will never be justified by any
behavior to the point as the world would say even
to the point as the world would say even
if highway robbers are sowing your limbs
one by one extremely unjust behavior
killing you basically if you have
cruelty and ill will towards them you
have not fulfilled the dhamma
doesn't mean oh it's fine for them to
cut your limbs it's not
it's unpleasant but you hating them is a
completely separate thing
the only person who is not free from ill
will person who hasn't fulfilled the
dhamma will jump into hence passion ill will
will jump into hence passion ill will
distraction delusion something you are
always responsible regardless of the
circumstances that are pressuring
seemingly pressuring you into it